So for this session, we
will look into another more
specialized application,
much like we
did with reinforcement learning
in the morning, and plasticity.
Now, we'll look into
decision making.
And we will build the circuit
that actually does decision
making in a behavioral task.
Now, a bit of some history notes
on the decision-making research,
and particularly, we will deal
with perceptual decision making
now with tasks that
have to do with evidence
accumulation over
time, and participants,
be it humans or animals,
having to decide
whether this perceptual
stimulus belongs
to one category or another.
Typically, there
are two categories.
But you can have tasks with
multiple possible answers
in any perceptual modality.
So and the distinction between
these perceptual decision-making
tasks and the previous tasks
that we saw category learning
is that with decision
making, and particularly
the perceptual decision
making, the categories
are known a priori.
So participants don't need
to learn by feedback, which
category is the correct one.
They just need to tease
apart any ambiguity
in the perceptual
stimuli by accumulating
more and more evidence
over time to reaching
a conclusion about
this stimulus seems
to be of the category A or B.
And I'd like to talk to you
about one family of models that
essentially started the boom in
modeling decision-making tasks,
or perceptual decision making.
That is the
drift-diffusion family.
You might have heard
of models like that.
So with drift-diffusion
models, to go over them.
How do they look?
What's the mechanisms
around them?
And what are the
first principles that
actually guided their creation?
And then we'll also look into
the random dot motion task.
This is a very popular
behavioral task,
purely perceptual again.
And then, we will also move
on to the second model.
That's the same model
that we will be building.
It's quite a popular model.
That's why we picked this one
from this one paper at 2002.
It can actually capture the
evidence accumulation dynamics
that the behavioral
DDM exhibits.
And it has some excitatory
population and one inhibitor
population.
And as you will see,
it also has a flavor
of this winner-take-all motif.
But in this case, the
structure is more--
it's more of an
abstraction over biology.
This network is not very
biologically realistic,
but it just gives us some
nice properties, because it
captures behavioral results.
And it can also explicitly
model different receptors,
as you will see.
Now, starting with the
drift diffusion model,
so as I was saying, there are
some principles behind it.
And you can find
mathematical derivations
of it, or the mathematical
proof, for this trade off
that I'm claiming here that
with the drift diffusion model,
it can optimally
negotiate this trade off
between accuracy and speed,
which means that if we ask
the model to be of a
specific accuracy level,
then we can tune it to
be the fastest model that
reaches that accuracy level.
By fastest, I mean, taking the
least amount of time gathering
evidence before
making a decision.
Or if you want a
model to respond
at a fixed amount of
time, and likewise,
a fixed amount of
evidence, then it
can be the most accurate model.
And essentially, the
model mechanism, you
can see a graphic of this here.
There's always
some starting point
in between two decision bounds.
And we have this
process that is, well,
the combination of a drift
process with some tendency
to go either up or down,
and some diffusion,
some additive noise
on top of that.
So you can think of it as a
particle moving across space
until it reaches one of
the two bounds, right?
And whichever bound it reaches,
then it makes that decision.
So this is the case of a
binary decision-making task.
So let's say that the
upper bound is left choice
and the lower is right choice.
And you can see colored, here
are all the free parameters
that we can use.
Starting point can
represent any bias
that the participant might
have any tendency towards one
category or the other.
And this is
particularly useful when
you vary the reward
that they might get
from one choice over the other.
Drift is the rate by which
they accumulate evidence.
The bound separation, that's
another free variable that
represents the
amount of information
that a person or an animal
needs to make a decision.
But there's also the
non-decision time.
And here, we can account for
any amount of the response
time that is not the participant
thinking about what they choose.
The typical explanation for
this is motor execution, right?
So because we make a
decision in our minds,
but then it might take some
few hundred of milliseconds
to actually execute
that decision.
So we can account for
that time as well,
and tease it apart from
the actual response time.
And now, moving on
to the experiment
that you will model in
a sense with a circuit,
it's the random dot motion task,
where essentially, a participant
sees this pool of
dots as they move
in space inside this aperture.
And they need to
decide essentially
what direction the dots
move towards, right?
Again, binary choices.
The dots move either on average
towards the left or the right.
And as the experimenter,
you can vary
the level of coherence
between dots, which
goes from 0% coherence, so all
dots move randomly, to some,
let's say 50% value, where as
you can see, half of the dots
move towards the
correct direction.
That is right.
And then 100% coherence is,
yeah, this is very clear.
So and this is a very typical
mechanism in perceptual
decision-making task, because
if the reward feedback is always
the same, then the
talents comes from--
and there is no learning, right?
The talents comes from telling
apart perceptual stimuli.
So you play around
with this ambiguity
and you can see
how participants,
be it animals or
humans, actually resolve
this ambiguity over time.
Moving on to the actual
model that you will work on
with the exercises.
So this is a schematic
of the model.
Essentially, there are two
excitatory populations,
A and B. Each one is
selective for one category.
But there is also some
non-selective neurons here,
also excitatory,
around this pool.
But now, the difference is that
the two selective populations
also receive specific
inputs to them,
representing any input
from upstream regions that
might signal one choice
being correct over the other.
So this is essentially
visual stimuli coming
in represented as IA or IB.
And there's also the
interneuron population here.
Of course, we always
need this feedback
between some
excitatory population
and some inhibitory ones,
as you saw in previous days.
And the interneurons
actually project
to both of these
populations, and
to the non-selective
excitatory neurons in here.
And on top of all this, there
is some background noise,
or some background
spike trains, that
represent upstream regions that
we're not explicitly modeling.
We'll just model them as
Poisson spike trains coming
into all of these neurons.
So here, I also
include the numbers
from the original model
from the Wang paper.
We will use a reduced,
scaled-down essentially,
version of this circuit.
But as you can see,
the scaled-down version
can still exhibit the
competition in one
of the two populations winning,
either A or B, and a decision
being made just by adding some
scaling factors to the model
parameters.
So and essentially,
as I was saying,
there is a selective current
coming into each neuron, the IA
and IB.
And we can, as you can
see here, essentially,
the two currents coming into
neurons for a level of coherence
that is, well, that is zero.
So this is why there is so
much overlap between the two
currents.
But yeah.
For instance, for a
level of coherence of 6%,
you can see the two currents
are actually split apart.
And here, we'll see
the distribution
of all potential current
values for IA and IB,
because the current
coming in is stochastic.
So we assume that it comes
from a normal distribution.
And we essentially set both
the new value and the sigma,
so both the mean and
the standard deviation
of that normal distribution.
So as you increase the
coherence more and more,
those two normal distributions
will come further
and further apart essentially.
So the currents will be
more and more different.
So decisions will
be easier to make.
And I just wanted to show you
the model equations in order
to highlight the fact that
this model explicitly includes
receptor dynamics in it.
So the first equation is just
the typical voltage gradient.
And it includes this
synaptic current.
And the synaptic current
has four terms in it.
One of them is just
the external input
that's coming in
that is representing
the visual stimulus.
So we assume that that
is an AMPA current.
But there is also some
recurrent AMPA currents
from other excitatory neurons
projecting to its neuron that
are recurrent NMDA
currents, likewise,
from other excitatory neurons.
And there is also GABA currents
coming in from the interneurons.
And you can see the
equation for each current.
There are simpler
ones in most cases,
except for the NMDA, which has
a bit more complicated dynamics.
And also respectively,
you can see the gradients
for the synaptic gates.
So each neuron has
a voltage gradient.
But it also has these synaptic
gradients modeling AMPA, NMDA,
and GABA explicitly.
So this is what I
was saying initially.
This model is not the most
biologically realistic
because it assumes this
wall-to-wall connection.
So the excitatory populations
are connected to one another
in a dense manner, and within
the neurons in a dense manner.
And you don't really
see this density
at high density in
actual brain circuits,
but it's a viable model because
it actually can actually
highlight the importance
of receptor dynamics,
and individual receptor dynamics
in the process of evidence
accumulation and
decision making.
And you will play around
with the receptor values.
And you will see how the
decision-making behavior
changes.
So these are some more results
from the paper that you could
replicate with the exercises.
So on the right here, we see
different coherence levels
starting from 50% going down
to an incoherent stimulus.
But even in the incoherent
case of 0%, as you can see,
these are populations,
say, A and B, right?
Both populations begin
firing in a similar manner.
But after a while, especially
this second dark line
here, one of them will win over.
So this one wins.
And the other one
slowly fades away.
A similar behavior to what
we saw before with winner
takes all and with the
pink model as well.
And this behavior is
even more pronounced
with higher coherence, with--
because with higher
coherence, it's
clearer to see from early
on, which one is winning,
right, because it also receives
a higher current to begin with.
So yeah.
Again, the same population
can win more easily
with at 50% coherence
compared to 0%.
And on the right here, we
see some essentially summary
statistics of this behavior.
You see some response
time distributions,
which are always a useful
metric, especially when you have
a perceptual decision-making
task, when the participants are
free to respond.
And you can also see some
more psychophysical curves
when the accuracy varies
over coherence values.
And yeah, this is
another typical result
from behavioral studies.
You can feed
sigmoidal curves on it
and use their parameters to
maybe organize your participants
into subpopulations, or to do
population-level statistics
between, say, a control
group and any test
group that you have.
So yeah, this was the end of it.
So feel free to
navigate from the course
to the decision-making
section, and then open
the decision-making notebook.
And yeah, as always, feel
free to ask any questions
that you might have.
So thanks.